Guide to the Dorothy Eisner Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dorothy Eisner papers
1923-2008
GEN MSS 778
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(2 boxes)
The Dorothy Eisner Papers consist of correspondence, photographs, and ephemera that document periods of her personal life and artwork. Eisner's correspondence files contain letters from fellow painters: nearly thirty from her friend Dorothy Andrews (1918-2008), who wrote mostly from her home in Khania, Crete; three from William Kienbusch (1914-1980); and one each from Sarah Freedman McPherson (1894-1978) and Emil Holzhauer (1887-1986); there are also letters from her stepdaughter, the painter Joan McDonald Miller. However, the bulk of the correspondence is between Eisner and her parents William and Florine Eisner, and includes letters in which she describes her interactions with Leon Trotsky during the Dewey Commission's hearing in Mexico City. Additional items related to that experience are the nearly fifty informal snapshot photographs taken in and around the hearing, Eisner's admission card, and one letter from Trotsky. Other friends in the correspondence files include the writers Tess Slesinger (1905-1945) and Diana Trilling (1906-1996). Other papers include copies of the constitution of the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, and an autobiographical memoir written by her grandfather Moritz Eisner, who had emigrated from Vienna to the United States. A folder of miscellaneous personal papers holds some childhood letters and drawings, a bank book from the early 1930s, and a few financial papers from the late 1970s-early 1980s. A binder of photographs and a scrapbook of clippings, photographs, and ephemera, supplemented by folders of announcements, brochures, and installation photographs, document Eisner's paintings and collages, and exhibitions of her work. The collection also includes two published books of photographs by Walker Evans.
Eisner, Dorothy
Eisner, Moritz, 1852-1938
Box 1
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Christie McDonald and Joan McDonald Miller, 1999-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Correspondence between Dorothy Eisner and her husband, and between the couple and their daughters, can be found in the John McDonald Papers (GEN MSS 622).
Dorothy Eisner (1906-1984)
Dorothy Eisner was an American painter whose career spanned more than five decades. She was born in New York on January 17, 1906, the daughter of Florine (1883-1974) and William J. Eisner (1880-1975). Though William Eisner was a businessman and manufacturer, he and his wife were also painters active in art circles in the city and in Woodstock, New York, where they had a second home. Their two children, Dorothy and Anne (1911-1967), also became artists, studying at the Art Students League then briefly in France, and spending a summer (1931) with other artists on Monhegan Island off the coast of Maine.
Dorothy Eisner met the writer John McDonald in New York in 1935; they were married on November 7, 1936, while each was employed by the federal government, McDonald with the Federal Writers' Project, and Eisner with the Resettlement Administration. The following spring the couple left their jobs and traveled to Mexico City with members of the American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky, a group of American liberals and intellectuals who supported the Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials (also known as the Dewey Commission after its chairman, John Dewey). While McDonald worked on Trotsky's administrative team, Eisner painted portraits of Trotsky and the hearing room.
With the exception of living in Croton-on-Hudson, New York, from 1942-1945, Eisner resided and had painting studios in the Greenwich Village section of New York City. She generally spent her summers painting in rural settings including Linville, North Carolina (1932-1935), Liebhardt, New York (1937-1942), Cape Breton, Nova Scotia (1947), and Livingston, Montana (1949-1958); the latter three were places to which she was introduced by her husband, an avid fisherman. From 1960 through her death, Eisner summered and painted on Cranberry Island, off the coast of Maine. She died in New York on April 28, 1984, survived by her husband, stepdaughter Joan (born 1929), and daughter Christie (born 1942).
Dorothy Eisner was a member of the Society of Independent Artists and the American Artists' Congress, and was a founding member of the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors. She also exhibited with the National Association of Women Painters and Sculptors.
Scope and Contents
The Dorothy Eisner Papers consist of correspondence, photographs, and ephemera that document periods of her personal life and artwork. Eisner's correspondence files contain letters from fellow painters: nearly thirty from her friend Dorothy Andrews (1918-2008), who wrote mostly from her home in Khaniá, Crete; three from William Kienbusch (1914-1980); and one each from Sarah Freedman McPherson (1894-1978) and Emil Holzhauer (1887-1986); there are also letters from her stepdaughter, the painter Joan McDonald Miller. However, the bulk of the correspondence is between Eisner and her parents, and includes letters in which she describes her interactions with Leon Trotsky during the Dewey Commission's hearing in Mexico City. Additional items related to that experience are the nearly fifty informal snapshot photographs taken in and around the hearing, Eisner's admissions card, and one letter from Trotsky. Other friends in the correspondence files include the writers Tess Slesinger (1905-1945) and Diana Trilling (1906-1996). Other papers include copies of the constitution of the Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors, and an autobiographical memoir written by her grandfather Moritz Eisner, who had emigrated from Vienna to the United States. A folder of miscellaneous personal papers holds some childhood letters and drawings, a bank book from the early 1930s, and a few financial papers from the late 1970s-early 1980s. A binder of photographs and a scrapbook of clippings, photographs, and ephemera, supplemented by folders of announcements, brochures, and installation photographs, document Eisner's paintings and collages, and exhibitions of her work. The collection also includes two published books of photographs by Walker Evans.
Arrangement
The collection is largely grouped by material type.
Art, American -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States; Moscow Trials, Moscow, Russia, 1936-1937; Painters -- United States; Women artists -- United States; Photographic prints; Artists; Painters; Andrews, Dorothy, 1918-2008; Eisner, Dorothy; Eisner, Florine, 1883-1974; Eisner, Moritz, 1852-1938; Eisner, William J., 1880-1975; Evans, Walker, 1903-1975; Holzhauer, Emil, 1887-1986; Kienbusch, William, 1914-1980; McPherson, Sarah Freedman, 1894-1978; Putnam, Anne Eisner; Slesinger, Tess, 1905-1945; Trilling, Diana, 1905-1996; Trot︠s︡kai︠a︡, Natalii︠a︡ Ivanovna, 1882-1962; Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940; Commission of Inquiry into the Charges Made Against Leon Trotsky in the Moscow Trials, New York, 1937; Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors
- Dorothy Eisner papers, 1.25; (2 boxes)
  - Card of admission to Trotsky hearing: Tarjeta de admision Miss Dorothy Eisner. Para las sesiones de la Comision Preliminar de investigastion de los cargos hachos contra Leon Trotsky en los jurados de Moscu. Presidente John Dewey [signed], Secretario Suzanne La Follette [signed]., 1937 (Box 1)
  - Photographs taken during the Dewey Commission investigating the Moscow Trials: 48 photographs including images of: Dorothy Eisner and John McDonald with Leon Trotsky; participants in the Dewey Commission including Herbert Solow, Jan Frankel, Albert Goldman, Jean van Heijenoort, as well as two of Diego Rivera with Trotsky; portraits of Leon Trotsky, inscribed by him to John McDonald and Dorothy Eisner; Eisner's painting of the Dewey Commission (now at the Dewey Study Center, University of Illinois, Carbondale); Eisner's portrait of Trotsky (now at Houghton Library, Harvard University); a lost painting by Eisner of Trotsky., 1937 (Box 1)
  - Encounter magazine issue containing a letter by Eisner about the Dewey Commission, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Review of Trotsky's The Revolution Betrayed, in the Evening Star, 1937 Mar 13 (Box 1)
  - Photographs of two paintings: "The McDonald House, Croton-on-Hudson, New York" (1943) by Walker Evans, and "Walker Evans Painting the McDonald House" (1943-1944), by Dorothy Eisner., undated (Box 1)
  - Dance International 1900-1937: exhibition catalog with Eisner drawings reproduced; letter of permission, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Ephemera from Eisner's exhibitions
    - Delphic Studios, New York, Mar 25-Apr 8, 1934:checklist (Box 1)
    - James Gallery, New York, Feb 17-Mar 10, 1961:advertising poster, checklist of paintings, and 15 installation photographs by Walker Evans (one signed) (Box 1)
    - Cisneros Gallery, New York, Nov-Dec 17, 1966: announcement (Box 1)
    - Cisneros Gallery, New York, Apr 5-25, 1969: announcement (Box 1)
    - Ashby Gallery, New York, May 17-Jun 6, 1980: announcement cards, signed catalog, notecard (Box 1)
    - Ashby Gallery, New York, April 16-May 6, 1983: announcement, review by Carl Little, press release, and photocopy of guest book (Box 1)
    - Farnsworth Art Museum, Rockland, Maine, May 3-Jul 5, 1992: announcement, catalog, reviews, slides (Box 1)
    - Announcements and brochures, 2005-2008
  - Biographic time line with exhibition histories, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Andrews, Dorothy, 1954-1983; 2 (Box 1)
    - Clark, Eleanor, 1959 Jan 8 (Box 1)
    - Eisner, William and Florine, letters from, 1925-1961; 2 (Box 1)
    - Eisner, William and Florine, letters to, circa 1925-1959, undated; 7 (Box 1)
    - Kienbusch, William, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
    - Letters from Linville, North Carolina, friends, 1932-1941 (Box 1)
    - Miller, Joan McDonald, 1956-1962 (Box 1)
    - Moore, Edie, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - Putnam, Anne Eisner, circa 1936-1962, undated (Box 1)
      General note
      Includes one letter from John McDonald about Dorothy Eisner and the Works Progress Administration
    - Slesinger, Tess, 1923-1938 (Box 1)
    - Trilling, Diana, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Trotsky, Leon, 1938 (Box 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1937-1984, undated; 3 (Box 1)
    - Letters to Florine Eisner (third-party), 1937-1951 (Box 1)
  - Drawings, undated (Box 1)
  - Holiday cards (printed) designed by Eisner, 1940, 1951, undated (Box 1)
  - Federation of Modern Painters and Sculptors
    - Constitution, 1940 (Box 1)
    - List of names and titles of works for exhibition, circa 1964 (Box 1)
  - Personal Papers, 1936-1982, undated; 2 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Moritz Eisner autobiographical memoir, 1936; mimeograph, undated (Box 1)
  - Christie McDonald, "Brushes with History"; offprint from Harvard Review, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Books by Walker Evans
    - American Photographs (New York: Museum of Modern Art), 1938 (Box 1)
    - Walker Evans (New York: Museum of Modern Art), 1971 (Box 1)
  - Oversize
    - Scrapbook relating to career of Eisner (assembled posthumously), circa 1927-1947, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs of art work by Eisner (in binder), undated (Box 2)